okay if not we can move to the uh
today's topic which is the RN transor uh
that is the uh I said the last uh the uh
architecture that we will explain uh in
addition to the hmm CTC and the
attention based encod
decoder okay so
um the RN transist is uh the one of the
uh end to end method so the uh
architecture is like this basically uh
similar to the CTC or attention based
encod decoder we try to directly uh
optimize P given W however this is the
different from the the ctcu or attention
and I will try to remark this kind of
difference in this
recor okay so I will review the
transducer which was already in
introduced in the beginning but in this
cases uh in that the timing I only kind
of explained about the very high level
so this time I will try to explain the
details about the the end
transducer so first uh the similar to
the all of formulation we always
starting from P the given o which is a
kind of all possible summation of the
alignment that becomes PW given o
right and please always remember that o
and the W are different lengths and O
will be the length of the large T
capital
T and the uh W token sequence uh Leng is
uh
J and in the uh RN transer uh we using
the the hard alignment variable Z
however uh this is the very different
from the the CTC or hmm and so on so uh
the especially lengths uh which part is
different from the RN trans
CTC in terms of the length of
Z yes t plus J right CTC cases it was t
but now the t plus J is the kind of a
the alignment variable that we have to
solve so this part becomes a plus J by
the way similar to the CTC we also
introduced the blank symbol or some
other people call differently but in
this lecture we call this additional the
symbol the is also the blank uh similar
to the uh name in the
CDC okay okay let's uh then formalize
formulate this uh the uh
equations so from the here to
here uh what kind of uh the uh Ru did we
use from here to
here product rule or chain rule right
and then actually uh this itself may be
uh the good to tackle
but instead of using this uh the
alignment uh the history as a condition
we usually using the the partial token
corresponding from one to K minus one so
and then instead of using the alignment
we actually add a change condition to
the partial token so this is a kind of
the basic uh the equation of the r and
transducer
and the let's also explain about some of
the definition of the function f inverse
is converting the the token sequence to
the all possible uh the the
alignment
okay and the uh one the f is actually
the inverse uh f invers is the the
function to convert from the the world
to the all possible Z and X is the
opposite function which is two they
represent the partial token sequence up
to K minus one and this one is a little
bit important so please also remember
this function and so
on and then similar to CTC or hmm we
have this summation over the sequence so
this part is the exponential but
fortunately we can actually using the
for backward algorithm to efficiently
solve this
one okay so this is the RN transducer
and I will explain bit more detail about
each kind
of characteristics with the
representation which you guys have our
paper now right so the please check the
uh the paper and then try to kind of
understand
it so so we usually using the this uh
the the
square ltis the information TR
information uh instead of the CTC and
this actually has the one big difference
which is that we have this kind of
Arrow this arrow is actually doesn't
change the
time and then we actually uh the output
to the uh token uh without the consuming
the time frame so please look at this
kind of a
pass start can start to use this
one
p so this
direction basically we don't consume the
uh the uh any of the
token and also note that the this the
formulation starting from the start of
sentence by the way this the graph
representation is actually a lot of ways
to exp explain about it maybe for
example starting the time from zero well
we can also using the the transition
based representation rather than using
this kind of a node based representation
but in this uh representation I just
following the notation of the original
paper we may find some better notation
but I just stick to the original paper
and so one so some cases for example why
this one is starting from tal one and
why this one is know the start of
sentence equal means that J equal
actually
zero uh this one is G equal Z J = 1 J =
2 J call
3 and this is not symmetric right this
one in the y axis starting from zero
while x axis starting from one but again
this is a kind of the convention of the
notation based on the original
paper and the our kind of the problem is
to find the the all possible path uh
from the left uh the corner to the right
corner and including the this final
State and so
on and as I said before uh the this uh
the the partical axis is very unique
which doesn't consume the input frame
and right side this is actually doesn't
change the state uh remaining in the
start symbol for example if we just kind
consuming
the uh the the uh time
frame uh this means that that we just
remaining to the the start of the
sentence uh doesn't output anything at
all at this
stage however to kind of reaching to
this goal we actually can have this kind
of
root and then we can actually uh the uh
the uh produce the the S uh the based on
this kind
of
root and I believe that we cannot make
make this kind of a transition in the
the CTC or hmm cases because then we
cannot reach to this uh end
CTC and the hmm always we try to consume
one other the the time stamp to move to
the uh uh the uh next the token but RN
trans this is allow so due to that
actually this the is very very flexible
uh compared with the uh the CTC or HM
based
approaches and then that we consider all
possible token that sequence and then do
some kind of inference or training and
so on that part is similar to the CN uh
CTC okay so now I will uh want to kind
of spend little bit the time to
understand the conversion of the
alignment and the to
so first as you may know the uh from the
given uh alignment
to to se this is actually many to one
mapping and how to convert from Z to W
this is actually quite simple we just
removing the the Brank symbol and the
first are the uh the the symbol and then
uh we can actually uh recover the uh
token sequence from the AL alignment
sequence uh so let's uh consider these
cases so this one is maybe you guys can
also write to do it by by yourself uh
starting from the S to
uh initial symbol to the
S and then next we will actually the the
the going to the consume the frame based
on the blank symbol
twice then we will move to the uh next
state
e and then we again again the using the
blank symbol to uh go to the right
twice and then finally we move to the uh
the output e and then the finish uh to
the goal so this is actually quite the
trivial the passes one of the trivial
passes to uh represent s e right and
then from the this part to this part the
the conversion is actually quite
simple we just removing the this
one this one this one this one and this
one and then we can actually recover the
other SE
SE actually the rule is more simple than
CTC right CTC cases we actually have to
uh take care about the consecutive
sequences but in this cases this is very
kind of the obvious that we actually
don't have to care about the consecutive
sequence and then we can actually get
the this kind of the the symbol without
using the some kind of complicated the
rules in
CTC so uh we can also do the same uh the
same cases this is little bit more
difficult and this is little bit
important part this is a partial
alignment uh let's say we are now uh in
the S2
sank
blank
E when we are at
here in this case the
um we uh can know the the partial
history are the at here and this partial
history actually becomes S and
E we just remove it okay so next uh is
that these also a kind of obvious but I
just want to explain about this by the
way this is
five okay so let's uh think about we
have some passes
right and then uh we have some kind of a
the point here let's say this point
D5 and as you see uh this is actually uh
the
information about the uh when this Z Z5
happens and then uh the which uh the
symbol D5 uh happens right so actually
given
if we have a kind of
passes all point we can actually get the
corresponding time frame and
corresponding the the output token so
this also the important the the the
function to understand the RN
transducer so basically RN transducer is
try to provide the probability for each
of these point this this is very
important so uh let's think about this
kind of the the uh problem and how to
realize uh this uh
the uh this other probability but again
the each of the let's the focus on the
each of the point and then we can think
about the compute some value and that is
our
goal however uh this is actually the
quite uh the
complicated two dimensional uh the vales
right so we could the F kind of a model
this kind of two dimensional values but
instead we try to actually use a very
simple ways to the provider score for
each the T and each token and so on how
to do
that first we just use the
encoder which is kind of the the getting
the
information of the uh
the uh over the token H sorry over the
time time frame right uh enoda is just
sweeping the all the kind of speech
features and then providing the
representation uh for each time frame
which we are studied in the acoustic
model in the spe condition CT or even
attention based and the G right and it
can be B
Transformer but in this case of course
we don't care about the
token we just try to get some kind of
features depending on the time frame now
we can do that by using the encoder
right and we do the same things uh for
the uh the the the partical
axis regardless of the acoutic
input let's try to uh prepare prepare
some token prediction uh the pro the the
functions how to model that we can just
using language model decoder Network
right so uh in this cases we actually
try to uh for example uh get the the sum
of the token the hidden State based on
the previously estimated hidden state
and previously
obtained the sequence and so on so by
using it we could actually deace uh this
kind of a condition other information
about a
token so note that again this one to K
minus one mean the sum of the
subsequence are the in the point right
and then we ignore the time stamp and
then we can compute the
the
dependency across the the token and the
dependency across the
frame and then how to make the sum of
the score that depend on both the time
frame and the token
position we can just combine them we can
just using these two features as are the
as
and then the predicting the next the the
the token which can include the bran so
one actually this function here is
approximated to right this kind of the
form we could by the way again use the
any other functions more complicated
function and so on this is actually one
of the approximation just one side of
the the information which is depending
the token we just using the the language
model and one side of the information
which depending on the time frame we
just using the a encoder and then given
this kind of a two other
information we can actually compute a
score that is actually the the what the
IR transer is try to model and here here
the since uh we want to make it the
probability first we want to convert it
the
score and then we using soft marks this
technique is also that quite often
happen in attention part right and we
just using this kind of uh the uh the
techniques to get the this information
to get the score which corresponding to
the the entire the partial the the the
history of this kind of probability so
this is
the the major part of the computation of
the RN transducer by the way how to
combine this one and how to get the
score I will explain it in the next
slide but anyway this is actually quite
other efficient we actually avoiding to
three sweeping this two dimensional the
information with are just the the two
times of the one dimens
the sweeping uh and also for the the
this part we can just using the encoder
Network which we already have a lot of
uh the studies there right and the same
for this part we just reusing the the
language modeling part I wrote here RNN
but of course it can be Transformer and
so
on okay uh this is the kind of the major
part of how to make make a condition of
the RN
transducer and then the last question is
the how to get to the score uh and so on
and the score can be uh by the way the
again
anything uh it can be actually the inner
product which we actually hard a lot of
experience in the self attention or
Transformer right but historically uh in
our
we using a little bit
complicated the this kind of form over
the the the a
combination this is because uh this the
soring part uh after the this other the
squaring part it just through the soft
Marx
function so if for example we using the
uh the simple uh the the the uh inner
product and so one in the product
doesn't have a parameter right so this
kind of a fusion representation is a
little bit
weak but by using this kind of
parametric form a fusion representation
is more flexible because we have a
parameters here we have a parameters
here and so on so uh this uh the uh
function form is the quite often used as
RN transistor or the scoring function
and this part is also called Joint
Network joint means that the in
information about the time frame
information about a token is a
considered jointly but this is for me at
a quite similar to the the attention the
score the based approaches although
there are several parameters and so on
and actually this part has not been so
much studied I would say some people
people actually are proposing to use the
multiplicative uh the one and some
people are actually try to use the Thea
inner product and so on and we may make
this part to be more complicated uh to
make the kind of joint Network to be
rich so this can be actually interesting
the research uh directions I feel but
anyway mostly people are using this the
additive uh the The Joint net work other
the
combination okay so that's the kind of
entire modeling with that now we can
actually represent this uh the the
function uh other uh the uh the neural
network the the
functions then uh similar to the uh the
CTC let's think about the
training and this part but uh if we try
to kind of directly uh working on the uh
the Arend transducer we have to care
about the summation over all possible
alignment sequence right but fortunately
AR and transer cases we can also compute
the forward and backward
probabilities and to how to make a
forward and or backward probabilities we
try to actually make a recursive
the equations right and in the our
transer cases we can also make decursive
the equation very simple okay uh very
simply so this is I just kind of the
taking the one part of the uh network uh
like you know uh let's say this
part let's think about I am kind of
taking the this part of the sub Network
here
and then we want to compute this
one and how to compute this one first
you know that if we have a this kind of
a function which we can uh obtain from
the previous step and then from here to
here we just are
multiplied by the uh the uh the uh blank
uh probability
and then uh this other the dot point is
going to the horizontal right the
direction okay so this is one way to get
the probability from this one and
similarly uh if we get the probability
from this
one we can actually compute the uh the
uh the probability of the partical
transition
in this case this can be a particular
the prediction the the token and then we
actually get some kind of a transition
probability so this uh the forward
computation is actually represented by
uh the two uh the the the ARs one is the
horizontal transition and the other is
the vertical
transition and then we can actually get
the for the computation and then since
this is recursive we can you know once
we have this kind of uh the probability
next one you know we using the uh the
next we want to compute this one we for
example Computing this one and this one
in
advance and then we can comp compute it
from
here and from here right
so we can actually also compute the the
four probabilities uh based on the r
trans
computation uh and then that we can
compute the loss or we can actually also
compute the some kind of inference score
and then performing the the speech
condition in the our
transer but uh I didn't kind of dig up
the the uh dig into the uh the details
in the end transer uh because it is very
similar to the
CTC and actually little bit simpler due
to uh this kind of uh the the AR uh
because of the uh the simple transition
comes from the the the RN
transducer okay so this is kind of
overall uh the architecture of the AR
transducer and again as I mentioned uh
this is it's uh based on the encoder
part which are providing the uh
information about the features for each
time
frame and this part is the I say very
similar to the RN the RN language model
or a neural network language
model and then this will providing the
hidden state of the uh token uh the the
previous token and so on
okay and then joint modeling is to
combine these other two variables and
then getting the score and then
providing the score uh in this other one
particular path in DK so this is the r
transist overview and as you could see
that there are lot of
similarity that compared with attention
based or TC based approaches right so
which I will spend some time and explain
it in the couple of
slide okay so first uh let's uh discuss
about RN transducer versus
CDC the biggest difference uh comes from
the conditional Independence
assumption by doing that we can actually
uh remove the uh conditional
Independence assumption and we can make
the RN transer to be more precise uh the
the uh that is kind of a most the unique
uh the the benefit of the RN
transer however uh the model is actually
in the RN transistor it is a little bit
kind of tricky especially the
um uh the com uh computation of of the
uh the training cost is actually larger
than
CTC so that is probably that easily you
guys can see that by checking this
one so please add a look at this one
which is corresponding to uh the get the
same token with a various the toties and
so
on so the question are the which
uh the which one has a more the the the
nodes uh that is related to the the the
other
transer uh and the
CTC let's check it one two three four
four times one two three four five 20
right this
one 11 so ctcs are the way smaller uh in
terms of the node and the number of ARS
I'm I didn't count it but I'm very sure
that CTC is less than the the RN
transistor and this number of ORS and
the number of uh the nod are actually
almost are proportional to the number of
computational
cost so due to that actually the r trans
computational cost is generally higher
than CDC
and RN trans is also similar to the uh
the uh the attention based encod decoda
we often use the teacher foring so this
is also another approximation so our
entres attention based encod decoder
generally that doesn't have so much uh
the approximation but they still using
the for the teacher forcing that is
actually quite large the approximation
okay so another part is that
CTC inference is actually the faster
than RN Trans in the most
cases because RN transistor has an
incremental computation part compared
with CTC right which part are the makes
the kind of computation the incremental
actually this are the decoder part token
prediction
part this part is since we have to wait
previous token uh and then other the uh
predict predicting the next token so
it's more like a language model so we
actually cannot make this part to be
paralyzed so CTC is actually
fter and the similar to the attention
based encod decoder I also want to
mention that RN transist is can use the
language
model but this the language model is the
not the very the
powerful uh since because the token
prediction part and the this uh language
model part is quite overed so it's
actually uh the doesn't will the
combined uh uh the language model scores
so RN transor has a lot of issues for
the using the shadow language model and
then as I mentioned some people is try
to kind of subtract the original decoder
language model inside the AR transer to
compensate this kind of mismatch and so
on so this is about the the RN trans B
CTC but of course there are lot of
approximation or kind of research to uh
the make the C RN transmissor to be
useful uh especially uh the when we try
to kind of use the this kind of to
structure as I mentioned this to
structure is very redundant and some of
the kind of a passes will not have to be
considered in speech
condition for
example the this
pass first you know goes to se
predicted and then consuming the all
frames this one is not very realistic in
speech equation right we just without
checking the speech features so much uh
generating the token and so on is
actually very uh
unnatural and the well basically even
you know other the other consuming the
token multiple times is not very natural
in the speech cases and then there is
The one extension of the RN transistor
which is actually the eliminate the
unnecessary
passes like this so in this cases we
just kind of arow uh the each kind of a
uh the uh passes to only get the the uh
the one uh the uh y the axis transition
token transition by doing that we
actually remove the many of the token uh
the the transition and then making this
uh the uh the out trans to be
simpler actually this is uh the the the
the one of the most the frequently us
the used alternative of the RN
transmissor which is kind of the
restricting the the emission of the
token per the one time uh that is quite
kind of the often used as an
approximation uh often during training
but sometimes even uh during the beam
search uh this approximation uh is often
used uh by the way uh since the the uh
RN trans user is uh very
flexible so do you guys remember that
the CTC cannot be used for the
TTS uh do you remember the reason why
CTC cannot be used for the uh
TTS yes exactly so input becomes
shorter uh than the output and then CTC
cannot reach the end right
in this case do you have this
constraint right you right actually even
you know one frame or or is
fine these are the possibly we can
actually emit all the token and the
reaching to the final the the position
so this is also very cool part of the RN
transistor uh we still kind of about uh
the assuming the monotonic behavior
monotonic assumption but the constraint
comes from the lenss is actually removed
in RN
transducer so I actually don't know but
probably some people using RN transistor
for CTC do you guys know this
work because theoretically possible so I
think it's very cool to do that yeah I'm
sure someone is doing it but I just want
to mention that again you know due to
the kind of uh the uh relaxation of the
ls uh the issues uh the RN transor can
be used for the just kind of a
assumption is just a
monotonic uh other than that we can use
many of the SE to se
task uh by the way uh our group is also
recently proposed uh another new CDC
which is actually includ ining the uh
the jump uh in the uh the transition in
the the the the horizontal axis which
actually reducing the computational cost
and making the kind of AR transes very
fast so this is also another solution
that we can find so basically uh not
only CTC in the CTC part we also I also
mentioned but not only CTC in the RN
transer by the the the the
considering some kind of a additional uh
the transition and so on we could
possibly build a new transer function uh
this this is what I want to also
emphasize so this part is not fly
fixed okay next uh comparison is the RN
transmissor versus attention
I actually try to write the attention
the very similar to the uh the AR and
transducer and actually this looks very
similar right uh where can you guys find
some Difference by the way from this
figure and from this figure in attention
and RM
transor correct while attention requires
everything right and then this part is
cross attention to consider all the the
speech featur while the RN transer is
more simple and then only taking the
feature here and then making the some
kind of alignment information and so
on so this is actually uh one of the big
difference of the RN transistor the
verus the attention and so on both are
based on the explicit conditional
Independence assumptions but
by using this kind of other information
actually RN transistor has a nice
property for online uh streaming
approaches by way CTC can also do it so
this other function is similar to CTC
but just kind of I want to emphasize it
the comparison with RN trans attention
Okay what I am talking about online
property online property here means that
we don't want to get to the Future
speech and then want to get the kind of
result in the
middle okay because uh if we are want to
get the future or the speech means that
we have to do everything after we finish
the something after we the Finish to UT
something
right uh if the computer very very quick
it may be fine but it can be very
efficient while I am speaking speech is
starting to recognize the speech
incrementally and unfortunately
attention it is not easy because again
we actually want to get this information
and we actually get all this information
after that we are using the attention to
generating the token sequence so
attention cannot actually uh we can make
it by using a lot of trick that the
online trick and so on but the generally
it is not easy to make attention however
in the RN transer cases very easy we
just kind of changing the
encoder not to checking the feature
context so we can just using you know
the unidirectional ldm or we can just
using the
the Transformer and so on and then we
can make this part not to checking the
future context right and by doing that
our transer can easily uh make the the
uh the uh the speech condition to be
working in the the streaming uh online
streaming manner so this is actually one
of the big reason that currently uh many
Industries are working on RN transducer
uh and the CTC and so
on okay so uh this kind of the uh the
end of the summary of today's the
lecture so Arn transmissor due to the
streaming property uh it is actually uh
the quite actively working in industry
and the many product are actually from
the uh the Aron uh right now and the
reason is because it is online and the
City is by the way can also make it
online but we can actually make the the
the trans generally better than CTC uh
thanks to the prediction
Network however I just want
to uh make some uh the discussions about
it so this is actually the a kind of
trend people are moving initially uh the
many people started to work on CTC
because it is
simple but the the later due to the
issue in the
performance uh the CTC R entrances
attention three of them are actually
compared in the the next phase and then
at that time actually attention was
better in term of
performance uh it has a drawback in the
online property but due to the kind of a
good performance and also having a lot
of uh the connections to the other areas
like NLP the computer vision and so on
attention was actually quite actively
studied but later uh the many kind of
instant industry started to work on the
RN
transducer uh because of the online
streaming the
capabilities and I say that this is our
current status so that I tried to put a
lot of emphasiz on the RN transer in
this lecture however we are not sure
next which one would be kind of I we are
still not getting the best kind of
solution of which one is better even hmm
maybe we can also include hmm uh we are
not sure which one is better because all
the technique has a pro and
cons and
actually recently many people started to
think that that we should move to the
attention uh because of the kind of a
strong other interface uh with the large
language models and so on AR transist
could use large language model from the
second pass or prediction network but
this is actually this are the the uh the
title integration compared with
attention based encod decoder because
remember that attention based encoder
decoder half the rest of the decoder
part is almost language model right so
it can have a very good kind of
integration while the r transistor is
through the joint model so joint model
is actually not so many parameters you
remember right so actually this part
eliminate the effect of the large
language model unfortunately so due to
that actually many people now ridit the
attention and so on and again also CTC
still many people are working on it so
uh this kind of a trend is changing but
in our lecture I try to kind of explain
all the kind of techniques so that you
know you can use each of the technique
for your
application okay that's it uh any
questions okay if not we can finish it
thank you